https://www.bnf.org/privacy-policy/

Skip to content
Privacy policy
27 August 2020
RPS
respect your privacy and are committed to protecting your personal data. This
privacy notice will inform you as to how we look after your personal data when
you visit our website (regardless of where you visit it from) and tell you
about your privacy rights and how the law protects you.
1. IMPORTANT INFORMATION
PURPOSE OF THIS PRIVACY
NOTICE
This privacy notice aims to give you information on how the Royal Pharmaceutical Society (trading as Pharmaceutical Press) collect and process your personal data through your use of this website (regardless of where you visit it from) and tell you about your privacy rights and how the law protects you. By visiting www.bnf.org (including the BNF and the BNF for Children app) and www.formularycomplete.com  you are accepting and consenting to the practices described in this policy.
This
website is not intended for children and we do not knowingly collect data
relating to children.
It
is important that you read this privacy notice together with any other privacy
notice or fair processing notice we may provide on specific occasions when we
are collecting or processing personal data about you so that you are fully
aware of how and why we are using your data. This privacy notice supplements
the other notices and is not intended to override them.
DATA CONTROLLER
These
Websites (www.bnf.org and www.formularycomplete.com along with the applications for the BNf
and the BNF for Children) are operated by the Royal Pharmaceutical
Society of Great Britain incorporated by Royal Charter in England and Wales under
company number RC00079 and having its principal business address at 66-68 East
Smithfield, London E1W 1AW (‘we’ and ‘our’) who also trade as Pharmaceutical
Press.
For
the purposes of the Data Protection Act 2018 and the General Data Protection
Regulation 2016, we are the “data controller” (i.e. the company who is
responsible for, and controls the processing of, your personal data).
We
have appointed a data protection officer who is responsible for overseeing
questions in relation to this Privacy Policy, including any requests to
exercise your legal rights. You can contact our data protection officer at:
Michael
Bonne
66-68
East Smithfield, London, E1W 1AW
data.protection@rpharms.com
You
have the right to make a complaint at any time to the Information
Commissioner’s Office (ICO), the UK supervisory authority for data protection
issues (www.ico.org.uk). We would, however, appreciate the chance to deal with
your concerns before you approach the ICO so please contact us in the first
instance.
CHANGES TO THIS POLICY
This
version was last updated in February 2020 and historic versions can be obtained
by contacting us.
It
is important that the personal data we hold about you is accurate and current.
Please keep us informed if your personal data changes during your relationship
with us.
THIRD PARTY LINKS
This
website may include links to third-party websites, plug-ins and applications.
Clicking
on those links or enabling those connections may allow third parties to collect
or share data about you. We do not control these third-party websites and are
not responsible for their privacy statements. When you leave our website, we
encourage you to read the privacy notice of every website you visit.
2. COLLECTION OF PERSONAL
DATA
Personal
data, or personal information, means any information about an individual from
which that person can be identified. It does not include data where the
identity has been removed (anonymous data).
We
may collect, use, store and transfer different kinds of personal data about you
which we have grouped together follows:
Category
Types of data
included
Retention Period
Identity Data
includes first name , maiden name, last name, username or similar identifier, marital
status, title, date of birth and gender,
2 years after your
last purchase or
access to the Website
Contact Data
includes your email address and billing address, delivery address, and telephone
numbers.
2 years after your
last purchase or access to the Website
Profile Data
includes
your username and password, purchases or orders made by you for any products,
your interests, preferences, feedback and survey responses.
2 years after your
last purchase or access to the Website
Demographic
Data job title and place
of work, sector of operation, job level and function
2 years after your
last purchase or
access to the Website
Technical Data
internet
protocol (IP) address, your
login data, browser type and version, time zone
setting and location, browser plug-in types and versions, browser error
messages, operating system and platform, and other technology on the devices
you use to access this website.
28
days – except
for cookies (Cookie expiry periods set out in our Cookie Policy)
Financial Data
includes any payment information and financial details you provide in order to use the
Website.
6 years after the transaction
Usage Data
information
about how you use our website, products and services
2 years after your last purchase or access to the Website
Marketing and Communications Data Marketing and Communications Data includes your preferences in receiving marketing from
us and our third parties and your communication preferences.
2 years after your last engagement with our marketing and communications.
We also collect, use and share Aggregated Data such as statistical or demographic data for any purpose. Aggregated Data may be derived from your personal data but is not considered personal data in law as this data does not directly or indirectly reveal your identity. For example, we may aggregate your Usage Data to calculate the percentage of users accessing a specific website feature. However, if we combine or connect Aggregated Data with your personal data so that it can directly or indirectly identify you, we treat the combined data as personal data which will be used in accordance with this privacy notice.
We
do not collect any Special Categories of Personal Data about you (this includes
details about your race or ethnicity, religious or philosophical beliefs, sex
life, sexual orientation, political opinions, trade union membership,
information about your health and genetic and biometric data). Nor do we
collect any information about criminal convictions and offences. We request
that you do not enter any special categories of data when using the interactive
features of our website. If you volunteer any special category personal data
whilst using our Website, we will process it in accordance with this Privacy
Policy.
IF YOU FAIL TO PROVIDE
PERSONAL DATA
Where
we need to collect personal data by law, or under the terms of a contract we
have with you and you fail to provide that data when requested, we may not be
able to perform the contract we have or are trying to enter into with you (for
example, to provide you with goods or services). In this case, we may have to
cancel a product or service you have with us but we will notify you if this is
the case at the time.
3. HOW WE COLLECT YOUR
PERSONAL DATA
We
use different methods to collect data from and about you including through:
Category of Data
Collection Method
Identity,
Contact, Profile, Demographic and Financial Data
You may give us your Identity, Contact and Financial Data by filling in forms or
by corresponding with us by post, phone, email or otherwise. This includes
personal data you provide when you:
apply
for our products or services; register
for and create an account on our website; email
us to discuss account management and services; sign
up for an event run by us or our affiliates; subscribe
to our service or publications; engage
with interactive features of our website, including groups and networks; request
marketing to be sent to you; enter
a competition, promotion or survey; or give
us some feedback report
a problem with our site including sending emails via the Zendesk support platform.
Contact, Financial and Transaction Data
Third party providers of technical, payment and delivery services such as WorldPay
Technical, Usage Data
Automated technologies or interactions with our website. We collect this personal data
by using cookies, server logs andother similar technologies such as Rollbar.
Please see our cookie policy for further details.
Technical
Data
Third parties such as
Analytics providers such as Google Analytics, based in the US. Search information providers such as Google, based in the US. Zendesk who provide our website troubleshooting services.
Marketing and Communications Data
Direct interactions when you tick boxes to opt in or opt out of marketing (through your account or by visiting the Website) and communications from us or unsubscribe to any of our communications.
4. USING YOUR PERSONAL
DATA
We
will only use your personal data when the law allows us to. Most commonly, we
will use your personal data in the following circumstances:
Where
we need to perform the contract we are about to enter into or have entered into
with you. Where
it is necessary for our legitimate interests (or those of a third party) and
your interests and fundamental rights do not override those interests.Where
we need to comply with a legal or regulatory obligation.
Generally
we do not rely on consent as a legal basis for processing your personal data
other than
Sending
email communications and newsletters about latest new drugs and significant changes,
insights and new products and services;
You
have the right to withdraw consent to marketing at any time by clicking on
links provided in our marketing emails and amending your preferences.
PURPOSES OF USE OF PERSONAL DATA
We
have set out below, in a table format, a description of all the ways we plan to
use your personal data, and which of the legal bases we rely on to do so. We
have also identified what our legitimate interests are where appropriate. Note
that we may process your personal data for more than one lawful ground
depending on the specific purpose for which we are using your data. Please
contact us if you need details about the specific legal ground we are relying
on to process your personal data where more than one ground has been set out in
the table below.
Purpose/Activity
Type of data
Lawful basis for processing
including basis of legitimate interest To register you as a new registered user
(a) Identity
(b) Contact
Performance of a contract with you
To process and deliver your orders on this website, for events and products, including:
(a) Manage payments, fees and charges
(b) Collect and recover money owed to us
(c) Direct Debit credit
reference checking. This information will be processed by Worldpay for e-commerce purposes
(a) Identity
(b) Contact
(c) Financial
(d) Transaction
(e) Marketing and
Communications
(a) Performance of a contract with you
(b) Necessary for our legitimate interests (to recover debts due to us)
To manage our relationship with
you which will include:
(a) Notifying you about changes
to our terms or privacy policy
(b) Asking you to leave a
review or take a survey including sending an email asking you to rate your
experience of using our products and services
(c) providing you with
information for and asking for feedback about an event you registered for on our site(a) Identity
(b) Contact
(c) Profile
(d) Marketing and
Communications
(a) Performance of a contract with you
(b) Necessary to comply with a legal obligation
(c) Necessary for our legitimate
interests (to keep our records updated and to study how customers use our products/services)
To enable you to partake in a
prize draw, competition or complete a survey
(a) Identity
(b) Contact
(c) Profile
(d) Usage
(e) Marketing and Communications
(f) Special Category
(a) Performance of a contract with you
(b) Necessary for our legitimate interests (to study how customers use our products/services, to
develop them and grow our business and to monitor equal opportunities)To administer and protect our business and this website (including troubleshooting, data analysis, testing,
system maintenance, support, reporting and hosting of data) and to ensure
that content from our site is presented in the most effective manner on your computer(a) Identity
(b) Contact
(c) Technical
(a) Necessary for our legitimate interests (for running our business, provision of administration
and IT services, network security, to prevent fraud and in the context of a
business reorganisation or group restructuring exercise)
(b) Necessary to comply with a legal obligation
To deliver relevantwebsite content and advertisements to you and measure or understand the effectiveness
of the advertising we serve to you)
(a) Identity
(b) Contact
(c) Profile
(d) Usage
(e) Marketing and
Communications
(f) Technical
(g) Demographic
Necessary for our legitimate
interests (to study how customers use our products/services, to develop them, to grow our business and to inform our marketing strategy)
To use data analytics to
improve our website, products/services, marketing, customer relationships and experiences
(a) Technical
(b) Usage
Necessary for our legitimate interests (to define types of customers for our products and services, to keep our website updated and relevant, to develop our business and to inform our marketing strategy)
To make suggestions and recommendations
to you about goods or services that may be of interest to you
(a) Identity
(b) Contact
(c) Technical
(d) Usage
(e) Profile
(f) Demographic
Necessary for our legitimate
interests (to develop our products/services and grow our business)
B. MARKETING
We
strive to provide you with choices regarding certain personal data uses,
particularly around marketing and advertising.
You
can also subscribe to receive newsletters, which will keep you informed, by
e-mail, of the latest new drugs and significant changes, insights and products
and services offered by Pharmaceutical Press. This can include: Newsletters
about MedicinesComplete, the BNF and Pharmaceutical Press, MedicinesComplete
Monthly, Medicines Information Products and Services, Research and Events
emails.
You
can change your marketing preferences by following the links on email
communications from us, which will take you to our marketing preference centre.
PROMOTIONAL OFFERS FROM US
We
may use your Identity, Contact, Technical, Demographic, Usage and Profile Data
to form a view on what we think you may want or need, or what may be of
interest to you. This is how we decide which products, services and offers may
be relevant for you (we call this marketing).
You
will receive marketing communications from us if:
you have requested information from us
or purchased goods or services from us and, in each case, you have not opted
out of receiving that marketing; andYou have subscribed to our marketing
email newsletters in the past; andYou opt in to receive the latest new
drugs and significant changes, insights and product/services information from
us.
We
use a marketing tool called Pardot, provided by Salesforce, that allows us to
automatically select relevant emails for you based on your sector and job
function or based on your activities on our website or subscription status.
You
may also be presented with Pharmaceutical Press marketing communications
through third party platforms that we work with such as Twitter and LinkedIn.
You can change your advertising preferences on those platforms through your
user account with those platforms.
THIRD-PARTY MARKETING
We
will get your express opt-in consent before we share your personal data with
any company outside the Royal Pharmaceutical Society group of companies for
marketing purposes.
SOCIAL MEDIA PLATFORMS
We
may work with other data controllers such as Twitter and LinkedIn to provide
you with targeted advertising about RPS whilst on those platforms. You can
change your advertising preferences on these platforms through your account
settings.
OPTING OUT
You
can ask us to stop sending you marketing messages at any time by following the
links on any marketing message sent to you or by contacting us at any time.
Where
you opt out of receiving these marketing messages, this will not apply to
personal data provided to us as a result of a product/service purchase
including registration for our applications, product/service experience or
other transactions.
COOKIES
You can set your browser to refuse all or some browser cookies, or to alert you when websites set or access cookies. If you disable or refuse cookies, please note that some parts of this website may become inaccessible or not function properly. For more information about the cookies we use, please see our Cookie Policy.
CHANGE OF PURPOSE
We
will only use your personal data for the purposes for which we collected it,
unless we reasonably consider that we need to use it for another reason and
that reason is compatible with the original purpose. If you wish to get an
explanation as to how the processing for the new purpose is compatible with the
original purpose, please contact us.
If
we need to use your personal data for an unrelated purpose, we will notify you
and we will explain the legal basis which allows us to do so.
Please
note that we may process your personal data without your knowledge or consent,
in compliance with the above rules, where this is required or permitted by law.
5. DISCLOSURE OF YOUR
PERSONAL DATA
We
may have to share your personal data with the parties set out below for the
purposes set out in the table in paragraph 4 above.
This
will include sharing data with the Royal Pharmaceutical Society and the
Pharmaceutical Press.Worldpay
assist in the processing of Financial Information for the purposes of
delivering e-commerce services.External
Third Parties as set out in the Glossary.Third
parties to whom we may choose to sell, transfer, or merge parts of our business
or our assets. Alternatively, we may seek to acquire other businesses or merge
with them. If a change happens to our business, then the new owners may use
your personal data in the same way as set out in this privacy notice.
We
require all third parties to respect the security of your personal data and to
treat it in accordance with the law. We do not allow our third-party service
providers to use your personal data for their own purposes and only permit them
to process your personal data for specified purposes and in accordance with our
instructions.
6. INTERNATIONAL TRANSFERS
We
share your personal data within the External Third Parties listed in the
Glossary (Paragraph 11) This will involve transferring your data outside the
European Economic Area (EEA).
Many
of our external third parties are based outside the European Economic Area
(EEA) so their processing of your personal data will involve a transfer of data
outside the EEA.
Whenever
we transfer your personal data out of the EEA, we ensure a similar degree of
protection is afforded to it by ensuring at least one of the following
safeguards is implemented.
We
will only transfer your personal data to countries that have been deemed to
provide an adequate level of protection for personal data by the European
Commission. For further details, see European
Commission: Adequacy of the protection of personal data in non-EU countries.
Where
we use certain service providers, we may use specific contracts approved by the
European Commission which give personal data the same protection it has in
Europe. For further details, see European Commission: Model
contracts for the transfer of personal data to third countries.Where
we use providers based in the US, we may transfer data to them if they are part
of the Privacy Shield which requires them to provide similar protection to
personal data shared between the Europe and the US. For further details, see European Commission: EU-US Privacy Shield.
Please
Contact us if you want further information on the specific mechanism used by us
when transferring your personal data out of the EEA.
7. SECURITY MEASURES
We
have put in place appropriate security measures to prevent your personal data
from being accidentally lost, used or accessed in an unauthorised way, altered
or disclosed. In addition, we limit access to your personal data to those
employees, agents, contractors and other third parties who have a business need
to know. They will only process your personal data on our instructions, and
they are subject to a duty of confidentiality.
Where
you have access to a secure area of the Website you are responsible for keeping
your login details and password(s) confidential and protected. We ask you not
to share your password with anyone. You can change your password at any time by
logging in. We accept no responsibility or liability if a third party obtains
and uses your ID or password. You must tell us immediately if you believe
someone may have access to or use of this information.
We
have put in place procedures to deal with any suspected personal data breach
and will notify you and any applicable regulator of a breach where we are
legally required to do so.
8. DATA RETENTION
HOW LONG WILL YOU USE MY
PERSONAL DATA FOR?
We
will only retain your personal data for as long as necessary to fulfil the
purposes we collected it for, including for the purposes of satisfying any
legal, accounting, or reporting requirements.
To
determine the appropriate retention period for personal data, we consider the
amount, nature, and sensitivity of the personal data, the potential risk of
harm from unauthorised use or disclosure of your personal data, the purposes
for which we process your personal data and whether we can achieve those
purposes through other means, and the applicable legal requirements.
By
law we have to keep basic information about our customers (including Contact,
Identity, Financial and Transaction Data) for six years after they cease being
customers for tax purposes.
In
some circumstances you can ask us to delete your data: see below paragraph 10
below for further information.
In
some circumstances we may anonymise your personal data (so that it can no
longer be associated with you) for research or statistical purposes in which
case we may use this information indefinitely without further notice to you.
9. YOUR LEGAL RIGHTS
Under
certain circumstances, you have rights under data protection laws in relation
to your personal data.
You
have the right to:
Request access to your personal data (commonly known as a “data subject
access request”). This enables you to receive a copy of the personal data we
hold about you and to check that we are lawfully processing it.Request correction of the personal data
that we hold about you.
This enables you to have any incomplete or inaccurate data we hold about you
corrected, though we may need to verify the accuracy of the new data you
provide to us.Request erasure of your personal data. This enables you to ask us to delete
or remove personal data where there is no good reason for us continuing to process
it. You also have the right to ask us to delete or remove your personal data
where you have successfully exercised your right to object to processing (see
below), where we may have processed your information unlawfully or where we are
required to erase your personal data to comply with local law. Note, however,
that we may not always be able to comply with your request of erasure for
specific legal reasons which will be notified to you, if applicable, at the
time of your request.Object to processing of your personal
data where we are
relying on a legitimate interest (or those of a third party) and there is
something about your particular situation which makes you want to object to
processing on this ground as you feel it impacts on your fundamental rights and
freedoms. You also have the right to object where we are processing your
personal data for direct marketing purposes. In some cases, we may demonstrate
that we have compelling legitimate grounds to process your information which
override your rights and freedoms.Request restriction of processing of
your personal data.
This enables you to ask us to suspend the processing of your personal data in
the following scenarios: (a) if you want us to establish the data’s accuracy;
(b) where our use of the data is unlawful but you do not want us to erase it;
(c) where you need us to hold the data even if we no longer require it as you
need it to establish, exercise or defend legal claims; or (d) you have objected
to our use of your data but we need to verify whether we have overriding
legitimate grounds to use it.Request the transfer of your personal
data to you or to a third party.
We will provide to you, or a third party you have chosen, your personal data in
a structured, commonly used, machine-readable format. Note that this right only
applies to automated information which you initially provided consent for us to
use or where we used the information to perform a contract with you.Withdraw consent at any time where we
are relying on consent to process your personal data. However, this will not affect the
lawfulness of any processing carried out before you withdraw your consent. If
you withdraw your consent, we may not be able to provide certain products or
services to you. We will advise you if this is the case at the time you
withdraw your consent.
If
you wish to exercise any of the rights set out above, please contact our data
protection officer at data.protection@rpharms.com or using the contact details
set out at the beginning of this policy.
NO FEE USUALLY REQUIRED
You
will not have to pay a fee to access your personal data (or to exercise any of
the other rights). However, we may charge a reasonable fee if your request is
clearly unfounded, repetitive or excessive. Alternatively, we may refuse to
comply with your request in these circumstances.
WHAT WE MAY NEED FROM YOU
We
may need to request specific information from you to help us confirm your
identity and ensure your right to access your personal data (or to exercise any
of your other rights). This is a security measure to ensure that personal data
is not disclosed to any person who has no right to receive it. We may also
contact you to ask you for further information in relation to your request to
speed up our response.
TIME LIMIT TO RESPOND
We
try to respond to all legitimate requests within one month. Occasionally it may
take us longer than a month if your request is particularly complex or you have
made a number of requests. In this case, we will notify you and keep you
updated.
10. GLOSSARY
LAWFUL BASIS
Legitimate Interest means the interest of our business in
conducting and managing our business to enable us to give you the best
service/product and the best and most secure experience. We make sure we
consider and balance any potential impact on you (both positive and negative)
and your rights before we process your personal data for our legitimate
interests. We do not use your personal data for activities where our interests
are overridden by the impact on you (unless we have your consent or are otherwise
required or permitted to by law). You can obtain further information about how
we assess our legitimate interests against any potential impact on you in
respect of specific activities by Contacting us
Performance of Contract means processing your data where it is
necessary for the performance of a contract to which you are a party or to take
steps at your request before entering into such a contract.
Comply with a legal or
regulatory obligation
means processing your personal data where it is necessary for compliance with a
legal or regulatory obligation that we are subject to.
EXTERNAL THIRD PARTIES
Amazon Web Services, based in Ireland and the US, who
provide website hosting and advertising services.Chrysalis, based in the UK, who provide market
research services.Firebase who provide
tools for tracking analytics, reporting and fixing app crashes, creating
marketing and product experiment.GoogleAnalytics who provide anonymised website usage
data analytics.GoogleAds, based in the US, who provide website
advertising services (currently based on content rather than personal use).Hedgehog Lab who provide
BNF app support and product development services.Highwire who provide login and access servicesusing SAMS SIGMA technologiesHM Revenue & Customs, regulators and other authorities acting
as processors or joint controllers based in the United Kingdom who require
reporting of processing activities in certain circumstances Instapage, based in the US, who provide website
management services to allow us to build landing pages for the Website.LinkedIn, based in the US, we upload data to
LinkedIn to allow us to target advertising that is relevant to youMDL MacMillan based in England and India, who provide
institutional and organisational subscription services to usMPS Ltd based in India, who provide business
services including processing of invoices and credit managementRedHat Inc, based in the US, who provide API
services which connect into the MedicinesComplete systemRedwing who provide IT, system administration
and customer mailing services using
CampaignMonitor.Rollbar, based in the US, who provide real-time
error tracking and debugging tools.Salesforce, based in the US,who provide CRM, document signing and storage services and who
provide Pardot which assists with
marketing services including emailing and website analytics.Survey Monkey for research purposesTwitter, based in the US, we upload data to
Twitter to allow us to target advertising that is relevant to youUsabilla who provide customer feedback survey
services WordPress who provide CMS, blogging and web
platform servicesZendesk, based in the
US,
who provide support and
workflow services.WorldPay, based in the US, who provide payment processing
services.
Top
MENU
Products
News
About
Consultations
Contact
This website uses cookies. By continuing to use the website you are giving consent for cookies to be used. For information on cookies and how we use them, please see our Cookie Policy.OKAYCookie Policy
